<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="32"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[IN]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[From the Publisher



                                                                      hank you for being a part
                                                                      of our first issue of SUSU
                    Contents                                     TCredit  Union Magazine,
                                                                 whether it was as an advertiser, a
                                                                 writer or just a well-wisher. This
                                                                 was  a  very  rewarding  venture
               3   Message from Minister of Finance              and one we will continue in
               5    Message from President -                     years to come.
                    Barbados Co-operative and Credit
                    Union League Ltd                             SUSU was sorely needed. Why
               7    Why the Co-operative Movement is Relevant     the name SUSU?  It has been said that credit unions

          9-10   History Of Credit Unionism In Barbados          got their start from ‘meeting turns’ or ‘susu’, and we all
                                                                 know what is a meeting turn; whether this is so, will be
             11     Appreciation – Brother Harcourt Lewis        discussed in our feature article.
           13-14   Credit Union Key Statistics
           17-18   Credit Union Bank                             We  hope  you  will  find  the  articles  informative  and
                                                                 inspiring as we seek to encourage you to continue to
             21   Operating Principles                           strive for the betterment of yourselves and our country
             25   Capita Financial Services                      by extension.
           27-28   Why Insure
                                                                 Looking forward to being with you next issue.

                                                                                                  Dalton Medford


                                                                 Contributors


                                          Credits                Jovan C. Medford

                                                                 Robert ‘Bobby” Morris
                                                                 Brother Keith Bourne
                                           Ad Advertising
                                          S.M Printing Services  Financial Services Commission
                                                                 Cecil N. McCarthy, Q. C.
                                   Magazine Coordinator          Capita Financial Services
                                          S.M Printing Services
                                                                 Anton Lovell
                                       Design and Layout
                                          S.M Printing Services  SUSU Credit Union Magazine is a publication of
                                                                 S.M Printing Services, Lot 35 Mount Pleasant,  St Philip



                                                                 Telephone:
                                                                 1 246 571 0170   •   1 246 262 0893
                     Disclaimer                                  Email: smpservices90@gmail.com



          The views expressed in this publication are the views of the writers and not necessarily those of SUSU © Credit Union
          Magazine. S.M Printing Services accepts no liability with regards to the messages carried by the advertisers or contributors.


                                                                                         SUSU Credit Union Magazine 1]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[2  SUSU Credit Union Magazine]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[While  credit  unions  remain  unique  and  can  boast  of  being
                    Minister of Finance and Economic Affairs
                                                                 the  only  financial  institutions  which  offer  patronage  rebates
                                                                 to members, they striven to ensure that in keeping with co-
                                                                 operative principles some of the surplus gained is translated to
                                                                 additional benefits and improved service for members. This is a
                                                                 step in the right direction and one that should continue to be
                                                                 strongly encouraged by the sectors’s leadership.

                                                                 With this in mind, one cannot help but admire the wide range
                 Message                                         machines, online and telephone banking services, investment
                                                                 of financial products and services including savings accounts
                                                                 in  many  forms,  loans  and  credit  facilities,  automated  teller

                                                                 instruments,  retirement  products,  bill  payment  services,  and
                                                                 financial  education  opportunities  that  credit  unions  now
                                                                 offer their very diverse and demanding membership. Indeed
                                                                 the movement’s participation in the local Carifs Network has
                                                                 expanded  the  ability  of  members  to  readily  access  financial
                                                                 resources through several automated teller machines across
                                                                 the island.
                     The Hon. Christopher Sinckler, M.P.
          Permit me to start by extending my heartiest           There is much of which we can be justifiably proud.
          congratulations to the publisher and his team of contributors   Even so the movement’s leadership cannot be content to sit
          for bringing to us this most educational and exciting magazine.   on their laurels. Rather directors across the sector must seek
          Your efforts in focusing on this very critical sector in our local   to implement and follow standards that would provide for the
          economy cannot be over-stated as it is not just timely but   maintenance of good financial health within their organizations
          essential to the process of public engagement and education   so as to continue to realise their full potential and contribute
          on and about this vibrant part of our financial architecture.  to the socio-economic progress of your members.  This is
                                                                 important because despite the many positives, there will always
          When we examine the history of the credit union movement,   be challenges which will arise. Today, credit unions operate in
          we  discover  that  the  first  credit  society  was  formed  in   an extremely dynamic environment and in spite of the fact
          Germany in the mid-1800s in response to harsh economic and   that you are considered non-profit organisations, safety and
          social conditions which the working class people were facing at   soundness are paramount given your fiduciary duty. Oversight
          the time. Similarly, co-operatives were registered in Barbados   responsibility of assets totaling over a billion dollars is by no
          because of hardships being experienced economically and   means a minor task or one where complacency should be
          socially by our own working class. This is precisely why, within   allowed to set in. Given the significant exposure to credit risks
          that context, we must not forget the significant contribution   appropriate risk management frameworks are critical to the
          co-operatives were able to offer ordinary families by teaching   mitigation of financial and social peril.
          them the importance of thrift and the benefits that may be
          derived from pooling their resources.                  I encourage all stakeholders involved in the movement to
                                                                 focus specifically on prudent management practices for credit
          There has been remarkable growth in the credit union sector   unions’ operations.  This  would include  the development of
          over the last four decades; interestingly, Barbados’ credit unions   internal controls and policies, which should be developed at
          have always thrived during times of economic challenge. This   a  pace that is  consistent with  the growth and complexities
                                                                 of each credit union. Such measures would reassure member
          is testament to the unique ownership structure of the sector   confidence and ensure long-term viability.
          and the fact that you, the owners, are motivated by access to
          quality service at reasonable costs rather than by the profit   Credit unions have helped to positively change the lives of
          motive evident in non-co-operative corporate structures.   many individuals in Barbados, across the region, and indeed
                                                                 throughout the world. They have allowed many working class
          Behind this very progressive philosophy, the credit union   people to fulfill their dreams of owning homes or expanding
          sector  has grown exponentially over the last decade with   them, providing private transportation, assisting in the education
          membership increasing from approximately 123,952 at March   of their children and generally improving their standard of living.
          2005, to 170, 049 at March 2015. During this same period,
          the asset base increased from approximately $788.2 million to   Long may this continue.
          $1.8 billion; gross loans to members grew from $592.8 million
          to $1.4 billion.                                       Thank you.

                                                                                         SUSU Credit Union Magazine 3]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[BARBADOS CO-OPERATIVE


                                                            &
                                  BARBADOS CO-OPERATIVE
                                BARBADOS CO-OPERATIVE
                               CREDIT UNION LEAGUE LTD.
                                                              &
                                                            &
                                 CREDIT UNION LEAGUE LTD.
                               CREDIT UNION LEAGUE LTD.
                                                 The Barbados Co-operative & Credit Union League
                                                 (“the League”) is the apex body for co-operatives.

                                                 The League is committed to supporting and
                                                  The Barbados Co-operative & Credit Union League
                                                The Barbados Co-operative & Credit Union League
                                                 developing co-operatives and building the profile of
                                                  (“the League”) is the apex body for co-operatives.
                                                (“the League”) is the apex body for co-operatives.
                                                 the movement.


                                                  The League is committed to supporting and
                                                The League is committed to supporting and
                                                 Services:
                                                  developing co-operatives and building the profile of
                                                developing co-operatives and building the profile of
                                                  o  Advocacy (Legislation, Regulation)
                                                  the movement.
                                                the movement.
                                                  o  Training

                                                  o  Mutual Benefits Plan (MBP) Insurance
                                                  Services:
                                                Services:
                                                     Administration
                                                   o  Advocacy (Legislation, Regulation)
                                                 o  Advocacy (Legislation, Regulation)
                                                  o  Technical Assistance
                                                   o  Training
                                                 o  Training
                                                  o  Financial Services (through the Central Fund
                                                   o  Mutual Benefits Plan (MBP) Insurance
                                                 o  Mutual Benefits Plan (MBP) Insurance
                                                     Facility Trust)
                                                       Administration
                                                     Administration

                                                   o  Technical Assistance
                                                 o  Technical Assistance

                                                   o  Financial Services (through the Central Fund
                                                 o  Financial Services (through the Central Fund

                                                       Facility Trust)
                                                     Facility Trust)
                                      st
                                     1  Floor, Co-operators General Insurance Building,


                                            Upper Collymore Rock, St. Michael


                                             Tel # 429-7075   Fax #: 436-5848


                                         Website:  www.barbadoscoopleague.org
                                        st
                                     st1  Floor, Co-operators General Insurance Building,
                                    1  Floor, Co-operators General Insurance Building,
                                              Upper Collymore Rock, St. Michael
                                            Upper Collymore Rock, St. Michael
                                              Tel # 429-7075   Fax #: 436-5848
                                            Tel # 429-7075   Fax #: 436-5848
                                           Website:  www.barbadoscoopleague.org
                                         Website:  www.barbadoscoopleague.org]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[Challenges
                                                                 There is compelling evidence that the quality of life that
             PresiDent  Message                                  negatively affected by a number of challenges.  These
                                                                 our members have come to expect and enjoy, has been

                                                                 challenges include but are not limited to developments
                                                                 such as our country’s economic down-turn, far-reaching
                                                                 regulatory regimes and  policies, and  more recently
                                                                 the passage of legislation resulting in taxes on our vital

                                                                 representation and protection of our Movement.
                         Barry Hunte                             assets. The League has been and remains steadfast in its
                         President of the
                    Barbados Co-operative &                      I invite you to reflect on these challenges and as you do,
                    Credit Union League Ltd.                     ask yourselves the following questions: Do we need this
                                                                 magazine and if so why? How will it make a difference?


                                                                 It is my humble submission that we need this magazine
                                                                 to help tell our story of how we make a difference in this

          Introduction                                           our critical journey as a Movement. The journey of which
                                                                 I speak did not begin with this publication; rather it was
          It is indeed a humbling, but honourable experience to   started through the vision, courage and dedication of our
          have been asked to write the President’s Message for the   founding members.
          first edition of The Susu (Credit Union Magazine).  As the
          umbrella body for the Barbados Co-operative and Credit   Through  saving, thrift and co-operation they created
          Union Movement, the League unreservedly welcomes and   our “susu”,  our  first  Savings  Society  and  continued  this
          supports this publication.                             journey that has transformed and enriched the lives of
                                                                 our members, their families and our Nation.
          Timely Publication
                                                                 Commendations
          The publication of this magazine is not only very important
          but also very timely since we as leaders over the years have   On behalf of the Board of Directors of the League, I take
          often lamented the dearth of written material about the   this opportunity to commend Brother Medford and his
          Movement. This publication helps to fill that void.  Moreover,   team  for  having  the  foresight,  confidence  and  belief  in
          it comes at a time when the Movement is confronted with   our Movement to drive the creation and publication of
          several unprecedented challenges. In the face of these   this magazine  which represents  another chapter  in our
          challenges there are a number of critical things which   journey. I therefore implore you to use this magazine to
          we need to do more effectively. This publication should   truly make a difference by telling our story, to speak of
                                                                 our birth mere decades ago and our phenomenal growth
          enable us to do two readily identifiable things. They are   through “MEMBERS HELPING MEMBERS”.  In telling our
          to (1) effectively communicate with, inform and educate   story, you must remain focused on the philosophy and
          our  members  and;  (2)  effectively  inform,  sensitize  and   principles which undergird  our great  Movement, which
          educate  policymakers and  other strategic  stakeholders   has made an outstanding contribution to our Nation’s
          about our existence,  and  the  invaluable  contribution of   growth and the empowerment of our large and diverse
          our movement to National development.                  membership.  I am obliged.




                                                                                         SUSU Credit Union Magazine 5]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[Jovan C. Medford is a 6th form pupil
                                                             of Harrison College and a Junimember of
                                                               Barbados Workers Union Co-operative
                                                                              Credit Union Ltd






         Why The Cooperative                                     (Natural Person Credit Unions). As such members of a Credit
                                                                 Union may work for the same company, attend the same

         Movement is Relevant                                    church etc. This is where the Cooperative Movement and
                                                                 Credit Union strives – when people who seek a common
                                                                 goal are able to work together to reach that goal. Imagine
               in Today’s World                                  the endless possibilities when people pool their resources
                                                                 together (as in a meeting turn or susu) to when they put their
                                                                 heads together resulting in large corporations existing for the
                 In a  world  such as  this,  where our  want  of   benefit of those involved and those to come. Evidence of the
          independence  far  more  exceeds  our need  of working   success of the Credit Union Movement in particular is its
          interdependence it is difficult for us to see the importance of   astronomical figures of membership. According to the World
          a movement which is deemed as “Co-operative.” The truth   Council of Credit Unions there are more than 57,000 Credit
          is we all wish to succeed. More often than not however, we   Unions, over 208 million members in over 103 countries.
          wish to  succeed  by  ourselves  and  for  ourselves. This is  a      Further, the impressive example set by the Credit
          limited view that restricts the effectiveness of one’s success   Unions has  also  been  expressed  at  the  corporate  level.
          as a tool for oneself as well as one’s society. As we say in   For example, Co-operators General Insurance Company
          Project Discovery, “How great are you if only you can benefit   Limited  (est.  1993)  is  locally  owned  by  the  Barbados
          from your greatness?”                                  Co-operative  Credit  Union  League  Limited  along  with  28
                 By  definition,  a  Cooperative  Movement  is  an   credit  unions.  A  notable  benefit  of  Credit  Unions  being
          organization whereby people organize themselves around a   shareholders in a company such as this is that profits from
          common goal. As is the focus of this magazine, the Credit   the company are distributed amongst Credit Unions and by
          Union will be used in this article as an example to show the   extension Credit Union members. Even more, Cooperative
          power and scope of the Cooperative.                    General Insurance Company Limited allows for a special
                 Primarily,  Credit  Unions  are  financial  institutions   discount for Credit Union Members.  These are the type of
          which seek to improve the standard of its members’ lives. In   perks that stem from working cooperation.
          the first instance, your Credit Union belongs to you. This is      In  Conclusion,  the  Cooperative  movement  is
          highlighted in the fact that you, amongst all other members,   indispensable to the growth of a nation. The movement is
          are involved in the election of the volunteer board  of   rooted  in the  concept  of taking  the  knowledge  of those
          directors which oversees the running of the Credit Union. In   who were privileged enough to take part in secondary and
          fact, you can compete for a position on the board yourself!   tertiary education and  melding  this with the experience
          As a result, Credit Unions can be described as democratically   and unorthodox creativity of those who learnt their lessons
          controlled financial institutions. This suggests that decisions   mainly from life itself. One of the most established forms
          made are made to the benefit of consumers as opposed   of a Cooperative is the Credit Union and its existence and
          to stockholders. Subsequently, Credit Unions price loans, pay   growth is a symbol to all that cooperation is achievable and
          dividends on funds deposited, and charge fees to provide you   beneficial.
          with high-quality, low-cost services including increasing your
          financial literacy through publications such as the SUSU as   Resources
                                                                  http://coopgeneral.com/viewnav.php?pg=aboutus
          well as seminars etc.                                   -www.caribefederal.com
                 In addition, earlier Credit Unions, many still today,   -Roos, Dave.  “How Credit Unions Work” 08 February 2008.  HowStuf Works.
                                                                  com. <http://money.howstuffworks.com/personal-finance/banking/
          were designed  for people  who share a common bond      credit-union.htm> 14 June 2015.


                                                                                         SUSU Credit Union Magazine 77
                                                                                         SUSU Credit Union Magazine]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[8  SUSU Credit Union Magazine]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[The Honorable Robert Morris
                                                              is Barbados’ Ambassador to CARICOM and
                                                              former Deputy  General Secretary  of the
                                                              Barbados Workers’ Union and a Historian











                                                                 stagnant growth in the pre 1960’s, and the acceleration in
           History Of Credit                                     the late 1970’s and the early 1980’s?

                                                                        The early image  of the credit  union as  a  poor
                                                                 man’s insitution, and overtones of welfarism restricted its
                  Unionism In                                    appeal to a small group. Provident societies like the Civic
                                                                 and the Chiming Bells, to name a few, manned by teachers
                                                                 and other enterprising persons was the dominant working
                      Barbados                                   class organization of the period.
                                                                        To some extent, there was an issue of trust, as

                                                                 some of the provident societies and the early credit unions
                                                                 had been subjected to criticisms of mismanagement and
                   The Financial Cooperative has proven to be    worse. Furthemore, a strong element of voluntarism was
            the most popular form of Cooperatives for Barbadians.   needed to galvanise the movement.  With the International
            Starting  from  humble  beginnings  in  the  1940’s  with   dedication of the decade of the 1970’s to the expansion
            the Shamrock Credit  Union, which  was the product   of the  credit  union,  the  room  for  both  associational
            of members of the Roman Catholic  Church, in 2013    and  community credit  unions expanded. In the  case  of
            there were reportedly 35 credit unions with 152,000   associational credit unions, those related to trade unions,
            members, with assets of $1.5 billion Barbados dollars.  mass based  bodies which provided  opportunities for
                   It is important to note that the period of 66   relationships with government workplaces  or organised
            years  between  1947  and  2013  was  not  marked  by   business to deduct membership contributions to savings,
            consistent growth and development. On the contrary, it   deposits,  and  shares,  there  were  signs  of  significant
            can be maintained that, for a long time, the credit union   improvements in the 1970’s and the 1980’s. In the case
            movement languished and  could not be  considered    of the Public Workers’ Cooperative Credit Union Ltd.,
            as being of national significance.There are discernable   associated  with the large National  Union  of Public
            trends in the growth of the movement: in 1961 there   Workers,  the  leadership  of  prominent  officials  like
            were 16 bodies, with less than 2,000 members; in 1966   Ralph Boyce and Keith Bourne, among others, contributed
            there were 25 bodies with 3,237 members, and assets of   to the development of what is the preeminent credit union
            $330,000; and by 1968, there were 27 bodies with 4,012   in Barbados. A similar phenomenon appeared across the
            members and $ 454,000 in assets. This period could be   pond in the Barbados Workers’ Union, where leadership
            seen as one of moderate growth. The period of the mid   at the level of the Secretariat under the inspiration of the
            1970’s can be characterised as one of stagnation, but   late Rt Excellent Sir Frank Walcott, and his senior staffers,
            between 1979 and 1983, the movement started on a     and Executive Council members like the now President
            path of accelerated development, which provided the   of the Union, Linda Brooks, and the then President,
            platform for the heights it has currently attained. By 1979   Lemuel  Daniel,  made  a  significant  contribution  to  the
            there were 26 bodies with 5,592 members and assets   development  of the  movement. The period  witnessed
            of  $3,996,000,  and  by  1983,  the  comparative  figures   other associational credit unions like those of the various
            were 37 bodies, with 11,750 members, and assets of    levels of the teaching  fraternity, and  of workplaces  like
            $16,023,000.                                         Cable and Wireless, and the Transport Board coming into
                   What factors were contributory to the relatively   their own.



                                                                                         SUSU Credit Union Magazine 9]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Enough recognition cannot be  given to  the     branches,  the  target  of  Government’s  fiscal  strategies
          relationship between sponsoring associations and related   and respect, banking type policies and large numbers of
          credit unions. In the case of the Barbados Workers’s Union,   permanent staff, has been the determination to employ
          the Executive Council of the Union allowed the paid staff   high quality  staff  with  a  combination  of loyalty  and
          time  to  function as  credit  union operatives,  provided   dedication to the ideals of the movement, as well as the
          rent  free  offices  and  equipment,  opportunities  for  use   intellectual capacity, and the skills that they possess.
          of facilities  for fund raising, and  allowed  organisers to      The League has provided a wider space for the
          include in collective agreements, provision for employers   exercise of skills for a talent pool created by the primary
          to deduct and forward savings to the accounts of credit   societies. Its indispensible services and offerings, at the apex
          union members. Such credit unions operated as recruiting   of the movement is symbolised in its new headquarters.
          grounds for trade union  membership, and in the early   In terms of symbolism, credit  union buildings at  Upper
          days, membership of the credit unions was restricted to   and Lower Broad Street, Fairchild Street, Speightstown, to
          trade  unionists  and  their  immediate  relatives. This was   mention a few places formally dominated by Banks and
          later expanded to membership, without affiliation through   white owned and controlled business tells its own story.
          membership of the trade union. Where trade unions did         1n recent times the movement has been asking
          not have medi-care schemes for members the credit      itself three very weighty questions. Should a Credit Union
          union also stepped in to fill the void.                Bank  be established?  Can  the union provide  venture
                 Of the community type credit union, the City of   capital  to help entrepreneurs? Should  the credit union
          Bridgetown Credit Union is the model template. Led by a   movement pave the way for other cooperative ventures.
          formidable group of University educated,  professional and      Extrapolating from the discourse on the growth
          youthful stalwards, without the benefits of the associational   of the credit  union,  we  can  assume  that  the  presence
          credit unions, Cecil McCarthy, Adrian Griffith, Oriel Doyle,   of motivation, skilled  leadership, legal  and institutional
          Winston Alleyne and Hugh McClean, among others had to   structures are preconditions for success in such ventures.
          depend on superb mobilisational and organisational skills,   The argument about whether the credit unions can sustain
          in addition to the mastery of the then new I.T.C. strategies   a Bank or a venture capital arrangement should depend
          to entice the denizens of the City to find a common cause   on whether there is a talent pool available to manage such
          to form a credit union.                                institutions successfully. Discussions about the differences
                 The  common cause that motivated  members       in charcacter of the institutions is a disguised method of
          was the strong desire to get access to credit. In the 1970’s   dodging  the true issue. Can a credit  union  sponsored
          and the 1980’s, land developers were making subdivisions,   bank compete with regional and international banks? That
          and governments were providing houses and housing lots   should be the major focus of the discussion. Do we need
          for building, but the banks were not friendly at the time.   farming  and  fishing  cooperatives?  Do  we  need  housing
          Furthermore, the ultimate consumer luxury for the middle   cooperatives? Services Cooperatives? These questions are
          class, the automobile was outside their reach, without the   really rhetorical, as there is a clear realisation that neither
          loan. The credit union provided the access to credit for the   the state nor the traditional private sector should be left
          growing middle class which, spurred by the free secondary   to these areas by themselves. As the credit union builds,
          education of the 1960’s had become the workers with    it is entirely possible that it will plateau in the near future.
          greater spending power than their parents.             It  is unlikely that  community credit  unions will expand
                 The strategy  of the Barbados  Labour Party     significantly,  and  associational  credit  unions  are  also  at
          in  amending  the  Income Tax Act  to  allow  credit  union   their plateau of success. The time is coming for the full
          members to benefit from taxfree savings would have been   diversification  of  the  cooperative  movement  to  impact
          a motivator but not the major cause of the burgeoning   the  future of our country towards  the  path  of greater
          membership in the movement.                            economic  empowerment. The credit  union movement
                 One of the major factors that  has driven the   must mount the discourse.
          movement to such a large membership base, expanding
















          10 SUSU Credit Union Magazine]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[Keith Bourne is a Retired Manager with the Barbados
                                        Public Workers Co-operative Credit Union Ltd and is now a
                                        consultant to the Barbados Co-operative and Credit Union
                                        League Ltd.






                                           Appreciation



            Brother L.V Harcourt Lewis in his inaugural speech as President of the Civil Service in 1968 said that one of his goals was
            to establish a Savings Society.  During this period, civil servants found it difficult to meet their financial commitments.  Brother
            Lewis was always concerned for the less fortunate in our society and, to this end, he and six other members of the Trade Union
            Executive having discussed the benefits of the society decided to inculcate the habit of thrift for civil servants.  An application for
            registration was submitted to the Registrar of Cooperatives which was approved.

            The Savings Society proved to be very successful having accumulated enough money to grant loans to its members. This time, an
            application was submitted to the Registrar of Cooperatives for the Savings Society to be registered as a Credit Union.  Unfortunately,
            the first application was denied, the reason given that there was already the teachers’ credit union whose membership bond
            was extended to all civil servants and therefore, there was no need to have a second civil servants credit union.  After months of
            deliberation, the application was finally approved and the credit union was registered on the 6th of May 1970.

            Brother Lewis was not satisfied that the credit union was meeting the needs of its members, in improving the social and economic
            wellbeing of its members,  since the cost of living was increasing at a faster pace than increase in civil servants’ salaries at this
            time.  In an effort to further relieve the financial strain he decided to establish a Buyers Club.  His aim was to provide an outlet
            for members where they can afford to buy basic essential commodities at lower prices than supermarkets and shops.  The Buyers
            Club was set up at the National Union of Public Workers and a group of volunteers would meet at the end of each month to
            distribute the groceries to the members of the club.

            In  1978,  when  Brother  Harcourt  Lewis  assumed  the
            Presidency of the Barbados National Bank, he continued
            to  serve on  the  Credit Committee  of  the  credit  union.
            At that time, the maximum loan a member could get was
            $1000.00 and members needed to borrow far in excess
            of $1000.00.


            In his capacity as President, he facilitated a strategic alliance
            with the credit union which allowed the credit union to
            approve loans up to $5000.00 per member.  The member
            was then given the appropriate documents to be presented
            to  the  bank  and  the  bank  would  disburse  the  amount
            requested.

            When the members became aware of the increase of the
            loan limit, the number of loan applications dramatically
            increased and this was followed by a further increase in
            membership which continued until today.

                                                                                         SUSU Credit Union Magazine 11]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[Credit Unions                                         Figure 1: Asset Distribution (In BDS $ millions)


               Key Statistics


                          Article 3





               The Financial Services Commission (FSC) is an
             integrated regulatory body, established on April 1st,
            2011 by virtue of the Financial Services Commission
                Act (2010), responsible for supervising and
                      regulating non-bank financial
                         institutions in Barbados




                                     Table 1: Number of Credit Unions and Total Assets





















          At the end of December of 2014, there were 35 registered credit   combined balance sheet for the credit union movement.  These
          unions operating in Barbados. The sector reported membership   loans accounted for approximately 75% of total assets, slightly
          of approximately 168,000 representing an increase of 4.3% over   up from 74% of total assets at the end of December 2013, but
          the comparable period one year earlier. For the same period,   below the average for the past six years of 77%.
          the consolidated assets of the sector were $1.75 billion up from
          $1.68 billion at the end of December 2013 (Refer to Table 1)   Consumer loans accounted for the majority of new loans
                                                                 issued to members (51%) followed by real estate loans (34%)
          Assets grew by approximately 4.2% between December 2013   and  transport  (14%).    For  the  twelve-month  period  ending
          and December 2014 to reach approximately $1,753.1 million   December 2014, new consumer credit increased by 9.7%, while
          (refer to Figure 1).  This growth rate was below the average   new real estate loans grew by 10.5% when compared to the
          of  6.0%  for  the  past  five  years.   This  increase  was  primarily   same period of the previous year (refer to Table 2).
          due  to  an  increase  in  net  loans  to  members  which  grew  by
          approximately $63.2 million or 5.1%.  As at December 2014,   Members’ savings which comprise both members’ deposits and
          net loans to members represented the largest asset on the   members’ shares increased by 4.8% going from $1,394.8 million


                                                                                         SUSU Credit Union Magazine 13]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[in December 2013 to $1,461.6 million at the end of 2014.  The   from 8.5% at the end of December 2013 to 9.4% at the end
          increase  in  members’  savings  was  primarily  as  a  result  of  an   of December 2014 (refer to Figure 4).  The change was due to
          increase in members’ regular deposit.                  an increase in the three to six months and 12 months and over
                                                                 categories of non-performing loans.
          As at December 2014, the capital to asset ratio for the credit
          union  movement  was  10.9%,  marginally  higher  than  the   Net income for the consolidated credit union movement for the
          10.6% reported at the end of December 2013.  The sector’s   nine months ended December 31, 2014 was $11.3 million (see
          capitalisation has trended upward slightly since 2010 due to   Figure 5).  This was 18.1% less than the net income recorded
          modest growth in equity and reserves (see Figure 3).   for the same period one year earlier.  The decline in net income
                                                                 was attributed to a slower rate of growth in total income (1.0%)
          The quality of the loan portfolio for the credit union movement   when compared to the rate of expansion in total expenditure
          declined  slightly  as  the  gross  classified  debt  ratio  increased   (4.3%).

                          Table 2 New Credit Issued – January to December (In BDS $ thousands)




















           Figure 2: Members’ Savings (In BDS $ millions)                        Figure 4: NPL Ratio



















                                                                    Figure 5: Income and Expenditure for the 9
                  Figure 3: Capital to Assets Ratio                 months ended December 31, 2013 (In BDS $
                                                                                     millions)

















          14  SUSU Credit Union Magazine]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[Cecil N. McCarthy
                                                                              is a Queen’s Counsel

                                 Credit Union



                                             Bank





          In May 2005, I participated in two exercises on the Caribbean    the Member State in conformity with the laws
          Single Market and Economy.  The first exercise was a seminar     thereof and which that State regards as belonging
          entitled “Caricom Single Market and Economy “Charting Our        to it, provided that such company or other legal
          Course in CSME” organized by the Central Bank of Barbados        entity has been formed for gainful purposes and
          held on May 5, 2005.  The second exercise was a panel discussion   has its registered office and central administration,
          on the “CSME Challenges and Opportunities for Credit Unions      and  carries  on  substantial  activity,  within  the
          in Barbados” sponsored by the University of the West Indies      Community and which is substantially owned and
          Alumni  Association (Barbados Chapter) and the Barbados          effectively controlled by persons mentioned in sub-
          Workers Union in which I was one of the presenters.  This        paragraphs  (i) and (ii) of this paragraph.
          discussion was held at Solidarity House on May 11, 2005.
                                                                 Mr. Duke Pollard (formerly a judge of the CCJ) made the following
          Both discussions caused me to read the Revised Treaty of   observations about the right of establishment in his book, The
          Chaguaramas and, in this article, I reflect on an aspect of the   Caribbean Court of Justice: Closing the Circle of Independence .
          revised treaty and its implications for credit unions.
                                                                 “The right of establishment has been expressed to include
          Chapter Three of the Revised Treaty is headed “Establishment,   the right to engage in any non-wage-earning activities of a
          Services Capital And Movement of Community Nationals”.  commercial, industrial, agricultural, professional or artisanal
                                                                 nature,  as  well  as  the  right  to  create  and  manage  economic
          One of the rights that will benefit nationals of Member States   enterprises within the contemplation of the revised Treaty.  In
          of the community as defined in the Revised Treaty is the right of   this connection, it is important to note that non-wage-earning
          establishment.                                         activities means activities of an economic nature undertaken by
                                                                 self-employed persons or independent contractors.  In order
                For the purposes of Chapter Three it is stated that:  to facilitate the right of establishment, Member States will be
                                                                 required to eliminate all legislative prescriptions and practices
                “a person shall be regarded as a national of a Member   which impede the exercise of the right of establishment. Such
                State if such person –                           constraining prescriptions and practices relate to the employment
                                                                 of managerial, technical and supervisory personnel in economic
                (i)     is a citizen of that State;              enterprises,  the  establishment  by  qualifying  companies  of
                                                                 agencies, branches or subsidiaries and conditions for entry of
                (ii)    has a connection with the State of a kind which   relevant personnel, their spouses and dependants.”
                    entitles him to be regarded as belonging to or, if it
                    be so expressed as being a native or resident of the   In the Revised Treaty the term “economic enterprises” is defined
                    State for the purposes of the laws thereof relating   to include “any type of organization for the production of or
                    to immigration; or                           trade in goods or the provision of services (other than a non-
                                                                 profit organisation) owned or controlled by any person or entity
                (iii)   is a company or other legal entity constituted in   mentioned in paragraph (a) of this paragraph”,


                                                                                         SUSU Credit Union Magazine 17]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[Credit unions are by definition organisations of members who   credit union movement, it is my view that the establishment of
          share a common bond.  These bonds are usually either based on   a commercial bank can be one of the most significant ways in
          community or geography or on occupation.  There are also often   which credit unions can put their stamp on the changing financial
          referred to as “not for profit” organisations.  I have detected no   market place.  And in much the same way as the CCJ has a dual
          specific wording in the Treaty which would make it obvious that   role as a court, with an original and an appellate jurisdiction, a
          co-operatives are specifically contemplated within the definition   bank established by and owned by credit unions can serve as a
          of right of establishment.  Here is an extract from my paper on   banker for credit unions and for credit union members and the
          “CSME – Challenges and Opportunities for Credit Unions in   public generally.
          Barbados”:-
                                                                 A broad range vision ought to see this entity as using the right
          “I myself am not so sure that credit unions are contemplated   of establishment to branch out to other areas of CARICOM at
          within the definition of rights of establishment in Chapter Three   some time in the future.”
          of the Revised Treaty.......

          I do believe however, that there is an indirect way in which the   Remarkably,  only  one  week  later,  a  similar  call  was  made  by
          credit union can in the medium term take advantage of the right   former Central Bank Governor, Sir Courtney Blackman while
          of establishment.  I think the approach should be to set up a bank   delivering the annual Olive Trotman Memorial Lecture sponsored
          which would cater to the needs of credit unions and members   by the Barbados Public Workers’ Co-operative Credit Union
          of the public including credit union members.          Ltd.  The former Governor saw this as a means of circumventing
                                                                 the inherent restrictions of credit unions as common bond
          The transfer of ownership in BNB and the Mutual Bank have   associations and facilitating competition with commercial banks
          created a void as far as indigenous banks are concerned.  This   on a level playing field.
          void clearly needs be filled and it is my view the credit unions are
          best placed to do so………                                Some ten years after my initial statement I still remain convinced
                                                                 that Barbados needs an indigenous bank and the credit union
          As  we  reflect  on  the  challenges  and  opportunities  for  the   movement is best placed to achieve that objective.]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[YOUR



                                                                                               BUDGET


                                                                                               FEELING THE
                                                                                         SQUEEZE?



                                                                                      We can give you an ease




                                                                           U.W.I. (Cave Hill)
                                                                           Co-operative Credit Union Ltd.
                                                                           We offer the financial services
                                                                           to cater for your every need.

                                                                            l Attractive savings and deposit interest rates!
                                                                            l Low interest rates on loans for business, housing/real estate and vehicles,
                                                                             charged on the reducing balance!
                                                                            l Tuition loans to qualified students at The University of the West Indies!
                                                                            l Loans to a maximum of $30,000.00 for the purchase of PV systems!
                                                                            l Your savings are insured to a maximum of $25,000.00 in the event of death!
                                                                            l Your loans are also covered to a maximum of $400,000.00 in the event of
                                                                             death!
                                                                        For further information please contact us at Tel: (246) 417-4524 or 417-4539

                                                                           Fax: (246) 424-0662  l Email: creditunion@cavehill.uwi.edu
                                                                            or visit us at our website http://creditunion.cavehill.uwi.edu


                      BARBADOS POLICE CO-OPERATIVE CREDIT UNION LIMITED

            •  Personalized member oriented services
            •  Loans up to $250,000.00                                                        Ask about our
            •  Special Loans (Line of Credit)                                              Mutual Benefits Plan;
            •  Competitive Interest on Deposits                                         Relieves beneficiaries of loan
            •  Demand Deposit Cash Accounts                                                 liability after death
            •  Attractive Fixed Deposits
            •  Junior Saver Accounts


           Tel No: (246) 436-9355
           Fax No: (246) 435-0788                          Convenient Parking
           Email: admin@policecoopcu.com                     Friendly Staff
                                                         Comfortable Ambiance
                                                 MEMBERSHIP OPEN TO

                         Members of Royal Barbados Police Force, BDF, Coast Guard and other
                                                        Security Forces

                                       Ex-members and Civilian Staff of the above

                                                  Relatives of members

              Carter & Hutson Memorial   Stop by, give us a call or visit our Website soon, to take full advantage of
           Scholarships available to members or         your membership
              children/wards of members.
                  Tenable at                        www.policecreditunion.bb.com
               UWI Cave Hill, BCC and
              other tertiary institutions.
                                               7KH )LQDQFLDO 6HUYLFHV <RX 1HHG )RU /HVV]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[SUSU Credit Union Magazine 21]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[Events playing at
                                                                                                •  Weddings
                                                                                                •  Parties
                          BET AD                                                                  Birthday,

                                                                                                  Christmas,
                                                                                                  Company
                                                                                                •  Cruises
                                                                                                •  Anniversaries
                                                                                                •  Graduations
                                                                                                etc.]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[Capita Financial


                                      Services Inc.,...





          ......while a relatively new name to the financial service sector, has   competitive  in  the  market  covering  preventative  care,  critical
          decades of experience in banking, lending and insurance under   illness, major medical with a built in life component.
          its belt through its diverse and experienced team.
                                                                 Capita’s collaborative strategy can also be seen at work in
          The company is unique in that while it is a banking institution, it   St. Lucia where they are currently engaged with the St. Lucia
          is owned by a credit union and has a subsidiary of its own that   Co-operative League Limited on a number of developmental
          brokers insurance.  It also has regional presence with offices in   initiatives targeted at the island’s Credit Unions.
          Barbados and in the OECS economic space through its branch
          in St. Lucia. This uniquely positions Capita to respond to a variety   On  the  corporate  side,  Capita  provides  an  attractive  option
          of market needs, not only across a wide range of consumer   for diversifying the investment portfolios of Corporates, other
          demographics including individuals, corporate and commercial   Credit Unions and even Government agencies, offering attractive
          clients but also across jurisdictions.                 rates on a range of investment products and over varying terms.
                                                                 Investor  confidence  has  grown,  even  outside  of  the  islands
          Since its introduction to the market in August 2010, Capita has   in which Capita operates with investors from other OECS
          amassed  total  assets  at  March  2015  of  BDS$200,000,000,  to   territories including, St. Kitts, St. Vincent and Antigua.
          quickly become the second largest tier three financial company
          in Barbados.                                           Additionally, on the lending side, with its experience in mortgage
                                                                 financing, Capita is also well positioned to assist smaller institutions
          The company is headed by Mr. Paul Maxwell who is supported by   such as smaller Credit Unions with the necessary funding
          Senior Account Manager (Loans) Mr. David Smith and Manager   required for their own mortgage portfolios, in both Barbados and
          of Finance and Planning, Mr. Michael Green while the brokerage   St. Lucia.
          operations are headed Operations Manager, Mr. Kenroy Mullins.
          Ms. Leona Cadette heads up the St. Lucia branch.
                                                                         Since its introduction
          Capita, which is primarily a mortgage company, has developed       to the market in
          a number of attractive mortgage and property products that
          are  constantly  in  demand,  namely  its  100%  mortgage  and  its   August 2010, Capita
          100% land loan; the maximum limits for these products are BDS
          $450,000 and BDS $250,000 respectively. In addition, Capita also   has amassed total
          finances larger land loans and mortgages both in the consumer
          and commercial sectors, vehicles and educational pursuits among   assets at March 2015
          others.
                                                                         of BDS$200,000,000
          These  finance  packages  are  further  complemented  with  the   to quickly become the
          value added insurance services though it’s full service brokerage
          in Barbados, Capita Insurance Brokers Inc., including life, health,   second largest tier three
          home  and  contents,  fire  and  peril,  marine  and  commercial.
          One of its most recent successes has been the Capita “four in   financial company in
          one” members’ health plan. This is a unique group health plan
          designed specifically for members of Barbados Public Workers’           Barbados
          Co-operative Credit Union Limited. This plan is one of the most



                                                                                         SUSU Credit Union Magazine 25]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[26  SUSU Credit Union Magazine]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[Books (Novels, Manuals, Poetry Books etc)
                                                           Booklets
                                                           Magazines
                                                           Calendars (desk calendars, wall calendars,
                                                           magnetic calendars etc)
                                                           Desk Pads
                                                           Annual Reports
                                                           Flyers
                                                           Labels
                                                           Posters
                                                           Print on Magnetic Paper (calendars,
                                                           products listings, safety guidelines etc)

                 Lot 35 Mount Pleasant                     Ad Design
                                                           Website Design
                       St. Philip BB18006
                                     Barbados              Banners (including Feather Banners)
                                                           Traditional Signs
                                                           Digital Signs
                                                           Van Wraps
                          Tel: 1-246-571-0170
                         Cel: 1-246-262-0893               Receipt Books
                                                           Delivery Books
                     smpservices90@gmail.com               Invoice Books





                                                                                         SUSU Credit Union Magazine 27]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[Anton Lovell
                                                                               ACII, ARM, Chartered Insurer
                                                                               General Manager of Co-operators
                                                                               General Insurance Company Ltd.











             Why insure?                                         to declare fully and truthfully all the material facts surrounding
                                                                 the subject matter of the risk they are seeking to insure.
                                                                 Insurance companies usually have proposal forms with pertinent
                                                                 questions  requiring  individuals  to  answer  truthfully  and  any
            Insurance is one of the most cost effective and reliable   misrepresentation of facts or untruths declared; in most cases
            methods of safeguarding one’s investment against the risk   will render the insurance contract null and void which result in
            of loss or damage; whether it is your business, your dwelling   claims not being honored by insurance companies.
            house, personal valuables or motor vehicle. It is one of the
            most effective risk management tools.                The insurance policy which is a vital part of the contract is
                                                                 very important and too many persons unfortunately opt not
            Insurance  is  a  risk  transfer  mechanism,  whereby  persons   to read their policies. Failure to do so in many cases, result in
            can simply pay a small premium to an insurance company   misunderstandings on the part of the insured person. The policy
            for  protection  of  their  financial  investment  against  loss   document details how the policy operates, the named perils that
            or damage resulting from specified perils. As part of the   persons are covered against and the policy terms and conditions.
            insurance contract, the insurance company is obliged to pay   Insurance  policies  act  as  creditable  security  for  financial
            claims on behalf of individuals suffering loss or causing loss,   institutions, such as Banks and Credit Unions which lend money
            damage or injury to others.                          to businesses and individuals, allowing persons to easily acquire
                                                                 mortgages, purchase stock and equipment, buy vehicles and pay
            Insurance  companies  rely  on  the  law  of  large  numbers,   for their children’s education.
            which means by insuring a large number of individual risks,
            it is not expected that losses will be suffered by all those   It is therefore said that a proper functioning economy usually has
            insured risks simultaneously. Insurance companies are then   a vibrant and robust insurance sector. It therefore makes good
            allowed to charge premiums which are far less in dollar   sense to consider an insurance policy when it comes to protecting
            value when compared to the dollar value of the risk of loss   your cherish family and your assets from an unexpected loss
            being undertaken. For example in Barbados, for every third   which could cause financial hardship and destroy years of hard
            party motor insurance policy undertaken by an insurance   work.
            company, by law the insurance company is exposed to a
            maximum of $30 Million Dollars in aggregate for third party
            death or bodily injury claims, in addition to $50, 000.00 for
            third party property damage claims (some companies grant
            as much as $1 Million Dollars). Policyholders obtain such
            coverage from insurance companies at an annual premium
            of less than $1000.00.

            Insurance companies compute premiums after receiving
            details of the risk being undertaken. It is therefore a major
            requirement of individuals purchasing insurance policies


          28  SUSU Credit Union Magazine]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[IN]]></page></pages></Search>